Guide to the Barbara Gair Scheiber Papers, 1942-1945
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Barbara Gair Scheiber Papers
1942-1945
Scheiber, Barbara Gair
0.3 cubic feet (1 box)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, news clippings, manuscripts and photographs relating to Scheiber's work with classmates Juliet Fleischl and Mary Draper in Clarion, Iowa, during World War II.
Biographical Note
Barbara Gair was a member of Vassar's Class of 1942. Directly following graduation, along with classmates, Juliet Fleischl and Mary Draper, Gair traveled to Clarion, Iowa, to organize and consolidate the various civilian war effort programs in the community. They helped to create the Wright County War Activities Council, then publised a number of articles offering the council as a model for other communities across the country. In the course of their war work, they were invited to the White House, met Eleanor Roosevelt as well as, then Vice President, Harry S. Truman.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, news clippings, manuscripts and photographs relating to Scheiber's work with classmates Juliet Fleischl and Mary Draper in Clarion, Iowa, during World War II.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Subjects:
World War, 1939-1945--Participation, Female; World War, 1939-1945--Iowa; World War, 1939-1945--Social aspects--United States
Places:
Clarion (Iowa)--History
VCL Categories
War and War Crimes
Encoding Information
Encoded by Jessica Kemm, September 2009.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Ted Avgerinos, May 2007 (M2007-011).
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence
- Series II. Writings
- Series III. News Clippings
- Series IV. Photographs
- Series V. Ephemera
Container List
- I. Correspondence
  - Gair, Mollie, June-July 1942 (Folder 2)
  - Gair, Mollie, Aug-Sep 1942 (Folder 3)
  - Powdermaker, Hortense, 1945 (Folder 4)
  - Telford, Betty, 6 Oct 1942 (Folder 5)
  - Publishers, 1944-1945 (Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1942, 1945 (Folder 7)
- II. Writings
  - Gair. "Pride and Prejudice On Main Street", (TS) (Folder 8)
  - Gair, Fleischl, and Draper. "Main Street Army", (TS) (Folder 9)
  - Gair, Fleischl, and Draper."Fighting Front on Main Street," National Municipal Review, 1943 (Folder 10)
  - Gair, Fleischl, and Draper. "Vassar Calls on Clarion," Threshold, 1943 (Folder 11)
  - Gair. "Lady Wearing Red Flowers In Her Hat", (TS of poem) (Folder 12)
  - Juvenelia (Folder 13)
- III. News Clippings
  - Originals, 1942, 1945, n.d. (Folder 15)
  - Photocopies, 1942, 1945, n.d. (Folder 16)
- IV. Photographs
  - Photographs, 1942, n.d. (Folder 1)
- V. Ephemera
  - White House place card, 14 Oct 1942 (Folder 14)